Kristaps J. Keggi Vietnam War service papers
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Kristaps J. Keggi Vietnam War service papers
1918-2018
1965-1966
Ms Coll 29
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
8
6 boxes and 2 oversize flat boxes.
Kristaps J. Keggi was a graduate of Yale and Yale School of Medicine who served as a surgeon during the Vietnam War in 1965-1966. He later became Professor of Orthopaedics at Yale School of Medicine. The collection contains contemporary correspondence, photographs, patient records (restricted), drawings of wound management, later reminiscences, and later drawings and presentation on Keggi's role in deveoping the anterior approach to total hip replacement, 1977-2018.
Keggi, Kristaps Juris, 1934-
Keggi, Julia Q.
Schlossberg, Leon
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research except for Box 3 which contains patient records that are restricted under HIPAA regulations.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Correspondence, photographs from Vietnam, and patient records donated to the Historical Library by Kristaps J. Keggi in 2013. Photographs and drawings on wound management donated ca. 1980 and 1983.
Arrangement
Organized in four series: 1. Correspondence. 2. Photographs and illustrated lectures. 3. Miscellany. 4. Patient records (restricted). 5. Oversized photographs and drawings on wounds and wound management in Vietnam. 6. Supplement, 2018.
Biographical / Historical
Kristaps J. Keggi was born in Riga, Latvia, in August, 1934, and arrived in the United States in October, 1949. He received his B.A. from Yale College, class of 1955, and graduated from the Yale School of Medicine in 1959. After volunteering for the Army in 1957, Keggi was commissioned as Second Lieutenant in the United States Army Medical Service Corps Active Reserve where he began weekly training. In 1959, he was promoted to First Lieutenant in the Medical Corps in the Inactive Reserve Berry Plan, which allowed him to complete his residency in orthopedic surgery at Roosevelt Hospital, New York City. Upon completion, Keggi was assigned his active duty as a Captain in the Medical Corps, United States Army Reserve where he was stationed at the Beaumont General Hospital in El Paso, Texas as a member of the Orthopaedic Teaching Staff. In spring 1965, Keggi was ordered to the 3rd Mobile Army Surgical Hospital (MASH) with the 173rd Airborne in Biên Hòa, Vietnam where he served as Chief of Orthopaedic Surgery from September 1965 to June 1966. Following his service in Vietnam, Keggi returned to Yale-New Haven Hospital as an orthopedic Surgeon and teacher in orthopedics. Since 1969, Keggi has also worked at St. Mary's Hospital and Waterbury Hospital in Waterbury, CT, where he has served as Director of Orthopaedics and Joint Reconstruction since 1992. In 2005, Keggi was the recipient of Yale University Athletics George Herbert Walker Bush Lifetime of Leadership Award. In 2010, Keggi was named the Elihu Professor of Orthopaedics and Rehabilitation at Yale University School of Medicine.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains letters by Kristaps J. Keggi, while serving in the Army Medical Corps in Vietnam from September 1965 to June 1966, to his wife, Julia Q. Keggi, who was raising their three young daughters in El Paso, Texas; letters from Julia Keggi to Kristaps Keggi; letters to Kristaps Keggi from his patients in Vietnam and patients' families; patient records from Vietnam (restricted); photographs of Keggi and family members; slides and digitized photographs from Vietnam and Bangkok, Thailand; photographs by Keggi of gunshot war wounds to the extremities and drawings by medical illustrator Leon Schlossberg, under Keggi's supervision, of these wounds and Keggi's methods of debridement and management; and news clippings and articles mentioning Keggi and the 3rd MASH.
A supplement to the collection, donated from 2013 through 2018, contains additonal materials related to Keggi's service in the Vietnam War and later materials on Keggi's work on the anterior approach to total hip replacement.
Gunshot wounds -- Treatment; Hospitals -- Vietnam; Leprosy -- Vietnam; Medical illustration; Medicine, Military; Mobile hospitals -- Vietnam; Orthopedics; Physicians' spouses; Rhade (Vietnamese people); Surgery -- Vietnam; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Medical care; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Personal narratives; Wounds and injuries -- Vietnam; Biên Hòa (Vietnam); Buôn Mê Thuột (Vietnam); Ho Chi Minh City (Vietnam); Drawings (visual works); Photographs; Slides; Orthopedists; Surgeons; Total hip replacement; Blount, Robert; Cadwalader, George; Keggi, Kristaps Juris, 1934-; Laier, Stephen, -1966; Price, John; Southwick, Wade; United States. Army. Medical Service Corps; William Beaumont General Hospital (El Paso, Tex.); Richardson, Mike; Yale University. School of Medicine
- Correspondence, 1965 September - 1966 June; Series 1
  Scope and Contents
  Contains letters to and from Keggi's wife, Julia (Julie) Keggi, in El Paso, Texas, during his time at the 3rd MASH in Vietnam. This series also includes official Army documents and orders, and later letters and e-mails from patients and patients' families. Much of this material has been recently annotated by Keggi.
  - Army documents, 1964 August - 1966 June (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Official Army orders to Vietnam; request to delay departure until after the birth of Keggi's daughter, Caroline; orders to Bangkok for R&R; discharge letters; and list of staff at 3rd MASH.
  - Letters from Kristaps J. Keggi to Julia Q. Keggi, 1965 September (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Contains letters to wife, Julie, and daughters, Katie, Mara, and Caroline, including details of his trip to San Francisco with Julie's aunt, Freddie, as well as descriptions of the arrangements in Biên Hòa, Vietnam. Letters include information about the types of wounds and procedures performed at the 3rd MASH.
  - Letters from Kristaps J. Keggi to Julia Q. Keggi, 1965 October (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Contains letters to wife, Julie, and daughters; a letter to M.L and J.V., Julie Keggi's parents; and a letter from General Blount to Julie in regards to Keggi's complaint about lack of medical supplies at the 3rd MASH. The letters describe volunteer services at the Biên Hòa Provincial Hospital, a map drawing of the area and details on a brief vacation in Saigon.
  - Letters from Kristaps J. Keggi to Julia Q. Keggi, 1965 November (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Contains letters to wife, Julie, with two attached newspaper clippings from the Saigon Daily News including a picture of Keggi and article on new weaponry. These letters also contain details on patients, patient stories and patient care as well as the conditions at the 3rd MASH.
  - Letters from Kristaps J. Keggi to Julia Q. Keggi, December 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Contains letters to wife, Julie, and a letter to Julie's father, J.V., as well as attached news clippings. Keggi provides a general description of some surgeries performed and stories about fellow staff members at the 3rd MASH.
  - Letters from Kristaps J. Keggi to Julia Q. Keggi, 1966 January (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Contains letters to his wife and family friends as well as various news clippings, including the visit of the Playmate of the Year, Jo Collins, to the 3rd MASH. He discusses the injuries sustained by Lt. John (Jack) Price and the excitement surrounding Price's introduction to Collins at the 3rd MASH.
  - Letters from Kristaps J. Keggi to Julia Q. Keggi, 1966 February (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Contains letters to Julie and various news reports of the situation in Vietnam, including the temporary relocation of the 3rd MASH to Buôn Mê Thuột. The letters include stories and articles about one of Keggi's patients, Stephen Laier, who underwent multiple surgeries before his death.
  - Letters from Kristaps J. Keggi to Julia Q. Keggi, 1966 March (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Contains letters to wife, Julie, about life at Buôn Mê Thuột, possible relocation, and the persisting lack of medical supplies. The letters discuss encounters with CBS reporters in Vietnam.
  - Letters from Kristaps J. Keggi to Julia Q. Keggi, 1966 April (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Contains letters to Julie about the return of the 3rd MASH to Bien Hoa and attempts at early release. Keggi discusses possible career changes and a move back to Yale following his service in Vietnam. Includes a photo of Keggi at the 3rd MASH.
  - Letters from Kristaps J. Keggi to Julia Q. Keggi, 1966 May - 1966 June (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Contains letters to Julie about plans to return home and future plans to teach orthopedics at Yale, along with continued descriptions of life in Vietnam. Also enclosed is a letter to Dr. Hubert Bradburn about the impending move to New Haven as well as a letter to in-laws J.V. and M.L.
  - Letters from Julia Q. Keggi to Kristaps J. Keggi, 1965 September (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Contains letters from Julie Keggi regarding life at home in El Paso with daughters Katie, Mara, and Caroline and babysitters Cello and Ophelia. Includes children's drawings from daughters Katie and Mara as well as photos of family members and a letter from her aunt, Freddie. Also contains news clippings about the war in Vietnam.
  - Letters from Julia Q. Keggi to Kristaps J. Keggi, 1965 October - 1965 November (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Letters from Julie discussing life at home, finances, and recreation. Includes children's drawings, photographs of family members, and news articles about Vietnam and life in El Paso.
  - Letters from Julia Q. Keggi to Kristaps J. Keggi, 1965 December - 1966 January (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Contains letters from Julie about life in El Paso, finances, the holidays, and reports on the children. Includes Christmas cards and news articles about various current events.
  - Letters from Julia Q. Keggi to Kristaps J. Keggi, 1966 February - 1966 March (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Contains letters from Julie with Valentine's cards, photos of the family, and news from home. Includes another newspaper article on Stephen Laier.
  - Letters from Julia Q. Keggi to Kristaps J. Keggi, 1966 April - 1966 June (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Contains letters from Julie about life in El Paso, the move to New Haven, finances, and the family. Also enclosed is a copy of a letter from Lucy Caldwell, a family friend working with troops in Vietnam.
  - Letters to and from patients and patients' families, 1965 December - 2013 March (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Contains thank-you letters from patients' families to Keggi and correspondence with patients following the war with annotations by Keggi.
- Photographs and illustrated lectures, 1965-2005; Series 2
  - Photographs of family taken to Vietnam, 1965-1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Contains pictures of wife Julie and children Katie, Mara, and Caroline, carried by Keggi at all times during his service in Vietnam. Also contains the 23rd Psalm, written in his grandfather's handwriting.
  - Photographs of Keggi and others during his time in Vietnam, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Contains three photographs of Keggi, 1965-1966, three images from Buôn Mê Thuột, and two much later photographs of fellow veteran and former patient John (Jack) Price and his wife at their son's graduation from West Point. All photographs are annotated by Keggi.
  - Photographic slides on Vietnam (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Forty-two 2x2 color slides used by Keggi in later lectures. They include the drawings in Box 4, images of war wounds, radiographs, and a few images of soldiers and scenery. Two slides are of a Rhade tribal initiation showing Keggi wearing a turban and loin cloth and holding a crossbow. See also Box 5, Folder 14.
  - Digitized Images from Vietnam, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Contains four disks (CDs) with photographs taken by Keggi during his time in Vietnam. Includes images of buildings, operating areas, war wounds, soldiers, and local tribespeople at the 3rd MASH in Bien Hoa and ban Me Thuot and during visits to Bangkok and Vung Tau. Of special note are images of Vietnamese people suffering from leprosy and cared for by a mission. Also included are the illustrations in Box 4 of this collection.
  - Lecture materials on war wounds in Vietnam, 1965-2005 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Two disks (CDs) containing audio, video and Power Point lectures. Includes Power Point presentation on treatment of soldiers and tribesmen in Vietnam, given by Keggi at the Walter Reed Army Hospital in 2009; and lectures at the Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences in Bethesda, Maryland.
- Miscellany, Series 3
  Contains miscellaneous articles and publications with annotations by Keggi.
  - Magazine articles on Vietnam annotated by Keggi, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Contains a Reader's Digest issue (May 1966) with an article on wound treatment that mentions Keggi and the 3rd MASH; and a National Geographic issue (January 1965) on Vietnam showing a tribal initiation similar to one that Keggi had participated in.
  - Miscellaneous publications and letters annotated by Keggi, 1918-2003 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Contains four articles, two by Keggi, and a letter to orthopedic surgeon Paul Brown, 2003, in which he describes his Army experience. There is also a published reminiscence by Playboy playmate Jo Collins of her visit to the 173rd Airborne Brigade, which Keggi described in his letters.
  - Curriculum vitae, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Patient records (restricted), 1965 September 18 - 1966 June 8; Series 4 (Box 3)
  Conditions Governing Access
  These records are restricted by HIPAA regulations because they contain patient information about named individuals.
  Contains the one-page "Clinical Record Cover Sheet" for each patient admitted. Information includes the patient's name, age, race, service, source of admission, diagnoses, how the injury occurred, and disposition of patient. Beginning with record 55, October 1965, there is a brief indication of treatment clipped to the cover sheet. In some cases, letters to Keggi from the patient or news clippings are attached to the record.
  - Records numbered 1-100, 1965
    The numbering appears to have been added by Keggi at a later date.
  - Records numbered 101-189
    At the end of the folder, there is a list of names of patients written later.
- Oversize photographs and drawings on wounds and wound management in Vietnam, Series 5
  - Color photographs of assault rifle wounds, 1966 May 4 (Box 4)
    Eleven photographs, 20 x 20.5 cm. According to Dr. Keggi, "The photographs were taken on May 24, 1966 at the 3rd surgical hospital ("MASH") outside of Biên Hòa. The wounds are those incurred by a Soviet Assault Rifle (AK 47) fired at almost point blank range."
  - Black and white drawings of war wounds and their treatment (Box 4)
    Four black and write drawings, 38 x 34.5 cm. The drawings in this and the following item were by Leon Schlossberg, medical illustrator at Johns Hopkins University, who worked in close collaboration with Dr. Keggi. They depict wounds to the extremities and their debridement and management.
  - Large color drawings of wounds and their treatment by Leon Schlossberg (Box 4)
    Six large color drawings 48 x 58 cm. See note to previous item.
  - Kristaps Keggi's publication using these images, 1970 (Box 4)
    Two copies of Kristaps J. Keggi and Wayne O. Southwick, "Extremity Wounds: A Review of the Vietnam Experience and Its Civilian Applications," in AAOS Instructional Course Lectures, vol. 9., St. Louis, C.V. Mosby, 1970, pp. 183-203.
- Supplement, 2018, Series 6
  Related materials donated from time to time by Dr. Keggi after the collection was first described in 2013. There is also material on Keggi's role in developing the anterior approach to total hip replacement, 1977-2018.
  - Additional Vietnam War-related material, Subseries 1
    - Photographs of drawings of war wounds and their treatment by Leon Schlossberg (Box 5, Folder 1)
      See Box 4.
    - Letters by Julia Keggi to her in-laws and photograph of Kristaps Keggi in uniform, ca. 1966 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Two letters from Julia Keggi to her in-laws, Dr. and Mrs. John Keggi in New York City. One is dated 1966 and the other is from the same period but undated. Photograph of Kristaps Keggi in uniform is ca. 1966 and annotated in 2015.
    - Mike Richardson, patient in Vietnam: recollections, photographs, visit to the Historical Library, 1966-2016 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Some of the photographs were taken of Keggi during the Vietnam War in 1966. Others are more recent, including the reunion with Keggi at the Historical Library.
    - Clippings, 1966 and 2004 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Notes by Dr. Keggi on an article about him in Yale Alumni Magazine, June 1967, 2015 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Keggi's annotation in 2015 of a brief article in this issue titled "Dissenting from the Dissenters"(pp. 12-13), that was about Keggi.
    - "Kristaps Keggi: Second Opinions of an Army M.D.", 1984 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Written by Joyce Banerjee and published in The New Journal 16[5] (March 2, 1984): 13-17.
    - Letters concerning Jack Price, 2008-2009 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      Concerning Price's claim for veteran's benefits concerning the gunshot wound in his arm that he sustained in Vietnam and that Keggi treated.
    - Jack Price's story of his arrival at the 3rd MASH in 1966, 2016 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Letter from George Cadwalader, patient in Vietnam, to Melissa Grafe, no date [2013-2016] (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Recollections from a former advisor to a Vietnamese Marine Battalion who became Dr. Keggi's patient in 1965.
    - Al Conetto, The Hump: The Fist Battalion, 503rd Airborne Infantry, in the First Major Battle of the Vietnam War, 2015 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Published by McFarland and Company, Inc., Jefferson North Carolina. Two copies, both annotated by Kristaps Keggi.
    - Articles from issues of the magazine VFW on the Vietnam War, 2015-2016 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Three issues accompanied by commentary by Dr. Keggi. The articles are about battles for which Keggi's group received the wounded.
    - Kristaps Keggi speech on Vietnam, 2017 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      This appears to be a speech to veterans at an occasion at which there was a march through Middlebury "to the tunes and beat of the Mattatuck Drum Corps."
    - Unedited pages of "Memoirs" concerning Kristaps Keggi's tour of duty in the Central Highlands of Vietnam in 1966;, photographs of gifts from the Montagnards (Box 5, Folder 13)
      Memoir draft dated 2018. The gifts from the native tribes in the photographs were donated by Keggi to the Peabody Museum. Folder also contains an issue of National Geographic, January 65, with an article, "American Special Forces in Action in Viet Nam" (pp. 38-65) which discusses the tribes in the highlands. Seee also Box 2, folder 9.
    - DVD: Kristaps Keggi, Vietnam Training Films: 1. Wound Debridement, 2. Debridement by KJK, 1975 and no date (Box 5, Folder 14)
      Contents: 1. M. Hamer, K.J. Keggi, and W.O. Southwick, W.O. (with technical assistance of Susan Wheeler), "Wound Debridement," presented at the Annual Meetings of the American College of Surgeons and the American Academy of Orthopaedic Surgeons in 1975. 2. Kristaps J. Keggi, "Debridement."
    - DVD: "173rd Airborne BDE. in Vietnam" (Box 5, Folder 15)
      Video about the 173rd Airborne Brigade in Vietnam published by Military Traditions Videos, no date. Keggi notes that the video shows "only one quick glimpse of what was the 3rd MASH. But it is a graphic view of our men and the conditions they encountered."
    - Drawings by Dr. Kristaps Keggi of war wounds, ca. 1967 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Later material on Kristaps Keggi's anterior approach to total hip replacement, Subseries 2
    - Illustrations for an article on leg length problems, no date (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Sketches by Kristaps Keggi for a lecture to residents, no date (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Articles on the anterior approach to total hip replacement, 1980-2004 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Kristaps Keggi's presentation on the book, The Direct Anterior Approach to Hip Reconstruction, 2016 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Kristaps Keggi presented "The Book--A Short Summary--in a Yale Contest" in the Historical Library, Cushing/Whitney Medical Library on May 26, 2016. The book was: B. Sonny Bal, Lee E. Rubin, and Kristaps J. Keggi, Total Hip Replacement with the Direct Anterior Surgical Approach (Thorofare, N.J.: Slack Incorporated, 2016).
    - Presentation, "Yale Surgery 'First': Anterior Approach to Hip Arthroplasty (1977), 2018 June 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Presentation was given in Fitkin Auditorium, Yale School of Medicine.
    - Drawings by Vicki Wilchinsky on the direct anterior approach to total hip replacement, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 3)